Guide to the Henry R. Luce Papers 1894-2004 (bulk, 1932-1967) MS 3014
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Biographical and Subject Files, 1916-2004 (bulk, 1930-1967); 205858; 17.6 Linear feet
  - Miscellaneous - Oskaloosa Citizenship, 1965, 1965-1966; 213594 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    Includes excerpts from speech by HRL to Time Inc. executives on May 4, 1950.
  - Miscellaneous, 1965, 213595 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    Includes a copy of a memo on the interview of HRL by Robert Shaehan regarding fundraising.
  - Miscellaneous, 1966-1967, 1966-1971; 213597 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    Includes a transcript of "A Profile of Henry R. Luce" from The Open Mind program on WNBC Television, and copies of materials found on HRL's desk following his death, including a letter from Marshall Berges with recollections of John F. Kennedy, letter from Hugh Sidey about his meeting with LBJ, and a memo regarding research on world poverty.
  - Miscellaneous, after 1967, 1969-1991; 213598 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    Includes a memo regarding HRL's thoughts on Time Inc. stockholders
  - Personal - Contributions - Political, 1936-1967; 213599 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    Includes copies of financial contribution lists and thank you letters from Richard Nixon and Barry Goldwater.
  - Personal - Contributions - Miscellaneous, 1937-1963; 213605 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Includes copies of lists of charitable and other contributions made by HRL.
  - Personal - Financial Ledgers (2 folders), 1945-1960; 213606 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
    Contains copies of ledger pages that have been taped together. Bottom page portions have been numbered in case they become detached.
  - Personal - Financial - Miscellaneous, 1946-1964; 213608 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    Includes a balance sheet of Clare Boothe Luce's Rome expenses.
  - Personal - Handwritten Notes, 1936-1967; 213600 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    Contains copies of handwritten notes (some transcribed) from HRL's desk in Ridgefield, CT and Phoenix, AZ on a variety of topics including philosophy, religion, and politics.
  - Personal - Memoir (Unpublished), 1966-1967; 213601 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    Includes preparatory notes made by HRL for his memoir and a 126 page manuscript.
  - Personal - Miscellaneous, 1943-1968; 213602 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    Includes copies of HRL's diary for 1940 and 1947, correspondence dealing with HRL's possible run for Senate, and a note "The Significance of the Goldwater Nomination."
  - Personal - Real Estate, 1935-1969; 213603 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    Includes a photograph of a house taken from about 500 feet in the air.
  - Personal - Recollections, 1964; 213604 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    Includes HRL's recollections of his personal involvement with eight Republican nominations for the Presidency and copy of notes from his 1964 trip to Asia titled "The Rim of Asia."
  - Additional Organizational and Subject Files, 222363
  - Air University Board of Visitors, 1959-1966; 221500 (Box 146, Folder 1)
    Includes a copy of the report of the 21st meeting of the board.
  - American Friends of the Middle East, 1953-1956; 221501 (Box 146, Folder 1)
    Includes copies of correspondence from Dorothy Thompson and John H. Shope.
  - American Friends of Vietnam, 1955-1957; 221502 (Box 146, Folder 1)
    Includes copies of correspondence from Angier Biddle Duke and John W. O'Daniel.
  - American Heritage Foundation, 1947-1954; 221503 (Box 146, Folder 1)
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (The Fund for the Republic Inc.), 1955-1967; 221504 (Box 146, Folder 1)
    Includes copies of correspondence and memoranda dealing with the Commission on Minority Housing, the Race and Housing Commission, housing discrimination, and the Luce Commission on a Free and Responsible Press. Also includes copies of correspondence with Robert M. Hutchins and a copy of what appears to be an article "Problems of Sovereignty and Nationalism."
  - China - United Service to China (and United China Relief), 1937-1943; 221591 (Box 146, Folder 2)
    Includes copies of the minutes of the Provisional National Committee of the China Emergency Civilian Relief and minutes of organization meeting of the Coordinating Committee for China Relief and Rehabilitation. Also includes copies of correspondence and memoranda dealing with the merging of various groups interested in helping China into the United China Relief, copies of fundraising letters, United China Relief reports, and copies of correspondence from James M. Speers, Mrs. Theodore Roosevelt Jr., Edward H. Hume, Pearl S. Buck, J. W. Decker, Joseph E. Davies, Herbert Hoover, Cordell Hull, John H. Reisner, Nicholas M. Schenck, Ronald H. Hall, and Walter Winchell.
  - China - United Service to China (and United China Relief), 1943-1958; 221595 (Box 146, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of the English translation of Generalissimo Chiang Kai-Shek's "Greetings to the Ardent Supporters of China Through United China Relief on the Occasion of the Thirty-Third National Day of the Republic of China," the reports "Five Years of United China Relief," copies of minutes of meetings of the Committee on American Activities of the United Service to China, a copy of a draft of the statement "An Appeal to Americans: Stand By Our Chinese Friends Now!," and "Private Philanthropy at Work in China: The United Service to China Program for 1948," original brochures "An Airlift of the Spirit" and "Plant Men!"; and copies of correspondence from Dr. Co Tui, B. A. Garside, and Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.
  - China - Aid Refugee Chinese Intellectuals, Inc. (ARCI), 1952-1959; 221597 (Box 146, Folder 4)
    Includes a copy of the minutes of the fourth meeting of the organization and reports of the Executive Director to the ARCI Executive Committee.
  - China Institute - 25th Anniversary Dinner on 18 May 1951, 221600 (Box 146, Folder 4)
    Includes an original program and invitation, and copies of speeches made by John Foster Dulles, Paul H. Douglas, and Dean Rusk.
  - China Institute - Miscellaneous, 1939-1952; 221617 (Box 146, Folder 5)
    Includes original pamphlets for the China Institute in America, and copies of memoranda regarding Chinese exchange students.
  - China Institute - Miscellaneous, 1953-1966; 221640 (Box 146, Folder 6)
    Includes original brochures from the China Institute in America, annual reports of the director, a copy of a memo dealing with a merger with The China Society, a memo from Charles L. Stillman on his impressions of Taiwan, a copy of a transcript of an NBC interview with Chiang Kai-shek, and a copy of the report "The Future of the China Institute in America" by William Henderson.
  - China - United Board for Christian Colleges in China, 1935-1963; 221643 (Box 147, Folder 1)
    Includes original pamphlets "Report of the Planning Committee, 1946" and "West of Okinawa...," and a copy of the report of the executive secretary. Also includes copies of correspondence from J. W. Decker, Robert J. McMullen, Carlton M. Sherwood, R. E. Diffendorfer, B. A. Garside, and Lloyd S. Ruland.
  - China - Tunghai Memorial Chapel (Taiwan), 1958-1963; 221652 (Box 147, Folder 2)
  - China - Miscellaneous, 1935-1967; 221653 (Box 147, Folder 2)
    Includes a copy of a draft of "The Luce Scholarship Foundation for Yenching University," text of a public statement by HRL commemorating the fourth anniversary of China's successful defense against Japanese aggression, a carbon copy of the "Formosa Report" from Kip Finch, correspondence from The Committee of One Million Against the Admission of Communist China to the United Nations, and original broadsides "Chapel for China." Also includes copies of correspondence from T. K. Chang, C. C. Hung, James S. Carson, William P. Gray, Helen Reid, H. C. Coleman, Jr., and William Henderson.
  - Comite International de l'Organisation Scientifique (CIOS) - International Management Congress, 1961-1963; 221654 (Box 147, Folder 2)
    Includes an original pamphlet "An Invitation to... The International Management Congress, September 16-20, 1963, New York City."
  - Council for Democracy, 1940-1942; 221655 (Box 147, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of the "First Annual Report of the Council for Democracy."
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1939-1964; 221656 (Box 147, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of the discussion meeting report of the Ad Hoc Group on Report to Senate Committee on Foreign Relations, and copies of correspondence from Walter H. Mallory, Percy W. Bidwell, Henry M. Wriston, Eli Whitney Debevoise, James W. Barco, and Hamilton Fish Armstrong.
  - Fair Employment Practice Code (FEPC), 1946; 221657 (Box 147, Folder 3)
    Contains copies of correspondence from A. Philip Randolph, the memo "Report on FEPC Lunch," and a draft of a form from Luce in support of FERC.
  - Famine Emergency Committee, 1946; 221658 (Box 147, Folder 3)
  - Federal Council of Churches, 1938-1951; 221660 (Box 147, Folder 3)
  - Fifty Million Fund (United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A), 1965-1967; 221667 (Box 147, Folder 3)
  - Hall of Fame for Great Americans, 1958-1965; 221673 (Box 147, Folder 4)
    Includes a copy of a letter from Ralph W. Sockman making Luce a member of the Electoral College of the Hall of Fame.
  - Hamilton College, 1961-1966; 221674 (Box 147, Folder 4)
  - Hotchkiss School, 1945-1966; 221675 (Box 147, Folder 4)
  - India League of America, 1944-1959; 221676 (Box 147, Folder 4)
    Includes a carbon copy of the message from Luce celebrating India's independence.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations (IPR), 1933-1952; 221677 (Box 147, Folder 5)
    Includes the brochure "IPR Facts and Figures," the newsletter Far Eastern Survey press release from the Preparatory Committee of of the American National Committee for Medical Aid to the Soviet Union and a memo from HRL stating his opposition, minutes of meeting attended by HRL, Edward C. Carter, James L. McConaughy, and Raymond Dennett, a typed note titled "Communist charges against IPR mostly in regard to American Council," and correspondence and memoranda dealing with the Communist influence in IPR. Also includes originals and copies of correspondence from Edward C. Carter, Philip C. Jessup, Lewis H. Brown, Douglas Auchincloss, DeWitt Wallace, Alfred Kohlberg, Brooks Emeny, Clayton Lane, and William L. Holland.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations (IPR) - Chronological Files (6 of 10 folders), 1940; 221679 (Box 148, Folder 1-6)
    Includes annual and biennial reports of the American Council of the Institute of Pacific Relations, report of the secretary to the board of trustees, press releases, a statement titled "The American Council and the War" issued following the attack on Pearl Harbor, agenda and attendee lists from an IPR conference, correspondence and memoranda dealing with fundraising and planning, a summary of discussions of the Joint Chinese-American Group, agenda and minutes of the annual meeting of the board of trustees, issues of the newsletters Far Eastern Survey and News of the I.P.R., form letters and announcements to the board of trustees and members of IPR, volumes from the Government Printing Office Hearings Before the Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary; United States Senate, Eighty-Second Congress, First Session on The Institute of Pacific Relations, statement presented to the Senate Judiciary Subcommittee on Internal Security titled "Fact and Fiction About the Institute of Pacific Relations," and drafts of the "Comments on the McCarran Subcommittee's Attack on the IPR."
  - Institute of Pacific Relations (IPR) - Chronological Files (4 of 10 folders), 1952-1955; 221758 (Box 149, Folder 1-3)
    Includes a volume from the Government Printing Office Hearings Before the Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate, Eighty-Second Congress, Second Session on The Institute of Pacific Relations, statements made at the hearings by Senator McCarran and William L. Holland, comments and replies to allegations, printed materials for distribution including "A Personal View of The Institute of Pacific Relations, 1925-1952" by Edward C. Carter and "Recent Letters Commenting on the Value of IPR," pamphlet "Some Issues in Japanese American Relations" and "New Books on Asia and the Pacific," and the newsletter Far Eastern Survey.
  - Korea, 1952-1966; 221759 (Box 149, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of a National Information Bureau, Inc. report on the American-Korean Foundation, and a copy of a letter from President Eisenhower.
  - Luce Foundation, 1957-1960; 221760 (Box 149, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1950-1967; 221762 (Box 149, Folder 3)
    Includes a carbon copy report on the history of the museum, and copies of correspondence from Dudley T. Easby Jr., James J. Rorimer, and Roland Redmond.
  - Metropolitan Opera, 1941-1955; 221763 (Box 149, Folder 3)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1940-1965; 221764 (Box 149, Folder 3)
    Includes copies of correspondence from Rene d'Harnoncourt, and Nelson A. Rockefeller.
  - National Presbyterian Church and Center, 1954-1972; 221765 (Box 149, Folder 4)
    Contains copies of correspondence, memoranda, and reports dealing with acquiring land, fundraising and construction of the National Presbyterian Church in Washington D.C. Includes copies of correspondence from Edward L. R. Elson, William S. Culbertson, Douglas McKay, Eero Saarinen, William V. Keenan, Joseph Newton Pew, Jr., George K. C. Yeh, Edward D. Stone, and President Eisenhower. Also includes an original program from the dedication of the Henry Robinson Luce Memorial Tower of Faith and a copy of the speech "The Faith of Henry Luce" delivered at the dedication ceremony.
  - National War Fund, 1944-1945; 221766 (Box 149, Folder 5)
    Includes copies of meeting minutes of the Executive Committee of the Board of Directors.
  - New York State Defense Council, 1958-1963; 221767 (Box 149, Folder 5)
  - Phoenix Art Museum and Fine Arts Association, 1960-1962; 221768 (Box 149, Folder 5)
    Includes an original certificate appointing Luce an honorary trustee signed by George C. Bright and F. M. Hinkhouse.
  - Preservation of Camelback Mountain Foundation (Phoenix), 1965-1966; 221769 (Box 149, Folder 5)
    Includes copies of correspondence from Barry Goldwater and Philip K. Wrigley.
  - Pro Deo (International University of Social Studies in Rome), 1953-1965; 221770 (Box 149, Folder 5)
  - Rockefeller Brothers Fund, 1956-1963; 221771 (Box 150, Folder 1)
    Includes a memo regarding a conversation between HRL and Henry Kissinger regarding the Special Studies Project, and a copy of a summary of minutes of the fourth meeting of the subpanel VI on "U.S. Democratic Process -- Its Challenge and Opportunity." Also includes copies of correspondence from Henry A. Kissinger, Townsend Hoopes, Nelson A. Rockefeller, and James McCormack, Jr.
  - Rockefeller Committee - Inter-American Affairs, 1940-1941; 221772 (Box 150, Folder 1)
    Includes a copy of the minutes of a meeting of the Policy Committee of the Cultural Relations Division.
  - Rule of Law, 1955-1967; 221773 (Box 150, Folder 2)
    Includes a list of individuals with whom HRL corresponded regarding the rule of law, carbon copies of a memorandum regarding a meeting with John Foster Dulles and a proposal for A Presidential Commission on the Rule of Law. Also includes copies of correspondence from Robert C. Storey, Charles S. Rhyne, C. D. Jackson, Frank K. Kelly, Elmo Roper, President Eisenhower, Arthur Larson, and Harold Shepherd.
  - St. Mary's College, 1951-1964; 221886 (Box 150, Folder 3)
  - Stanford University, 1952-1957; 221887 (Box 150, Folder 3)
    Includes a carbon copy of the report "Teaching Law in the Liberal Arts Curriculum" by Moffatt Hancock.
  - Union Theological Seminary, 1946-1966; 221888 (Box 150, Folder 3)
    Includes a copy of the "Report of the Special Committee on National Purpose."
  - Urban League, 1947-1964; 221889 (Box 150, Folder 3)
    Includes copies of the minutes of the meeting of the "Representatives of the Negro Press," transcript of the talk given by HRL on an NBC program, a letter from Lester B. Granger, and an original brochure "One Tenth of the Nation..."
  - Westminster College - Winston Churchill Memorial, 1961-1965; 221890 (Box 150, Folder 4)
    Includes a copy of a letter from Churchill to Robert L. D. Davidson and from Anthony Montague Browne to HRL, and a copy of a report to Churchill on a dinner held in his honor.
  - William Allen White Foundation, 1960-1963; 221891 (Box 150, Folder 4)
  - Wooster, College of, 1962-1966; 221897 (Box 150, Folder 4)
    Includes minutes of the meeting of the board of trustees.
  - Yale, 1935-1973; 221903 (Box 150, Folder 6)
    Includes correspondence regarding class reunions, Henry R. Luce Professorship in Jurisprudence at Yale, and the Yale Daily News newspaper. Also includes a statement from HRL on the 60th anniversary of Yale Daily News, drafts of untitled articles possibly by HRL and HRL's article "Careers in Journalism" for the Yale Daily News supplement. In addition there is a carbon copy of a "Proposal for the American Political Magazine," editorial prospectus for the Political Magazine with original correspondence from HRL, William D. Waddell, and Cletus P. Lyman.
  - Yale-in-China, 1946-1959; 221902 (Box 150, Folder 5)
    Includes a Chinese newspaper, a "Rebuild Yale-in-China" brochure, a signed letter from W. Averell Harriman to Allen Grover, Yale-in-China trustees meeting agenda, report, timeline and charts (all originals).
  - Organizations A-Z - Miscellaneous, 1935-1966; 221905 (Box 151, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence regarding the Academy of Political Science, American Committee to Assist Hungarian Freedom Federation, the Atlantic Council of the United States, Christ Church Blue Boar Fund, International Rescue Committee, National Conference of Christians and Jews, the United Negro College Fund, and World Council of Churches. Also includes an original newsletter of the Lotos Club Lotos Leaf with photographs of Henry and Clare Luce.
- Series II. Speeches and Writings, 1916-1967 (bulk, 1930-1966); 205861; 11.05 Linear feet
  The series is organized in two subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Working Files
  Subseries II.B. Final Speeches and Writings
  The series consists of working and final files of the speeches and writings produced by Henry R. Luce (hereafter HRL). Speech related materials make up the majority of the series.
  - Subseries II.A. Working Files, 1920-1967 (bulk, 1930-1966); 205866
    The subseries includes correspondence inviting HRL to speak or submit an article for publication; his responses and internal memoranda discussing what actions he should take; planning and scheduling the trip to give the speech; invitations to meet individuals unrelated to the speech located in the area to be visited; background and biographical information on individuals and organizations inviting HRL, on those attending the event, those he may meet, and information on employees working in the Time Inc. regional offices; background on the venue and events where he is scheduled to speak; arrangements for where he will be staying, and detailed itineraries.
    In addition there are a large number of heavily marked early and later drafts of speeches and articles, as well as the final versions; handwritten notes; speech outlines; reference and research materials assembled to assist the writing process or to be incorporated into the article or speech; internal memoranda requesting the opinions of Time Inc. staff and their responses, comments and advice. The internal memoranda and correspondence involving logistical planning, fact checking, and advice given to HRL is sent to and received from his secretary, Corinne Thrasher, and a number of personal assistants and Time Inc. officers including Allen Grover, Russell Bourne, Emeline Nollen, C.D. Jackson, Albert L. Furth, Wes Bailey, Bernard Barnes, and John Jessup.
    There are also brochures, programs, promotional materials, press releases and other printed materials from the events where HRL made the speech or that were published by the group which invited him; and responses and reactions from attendees, Time Inc. staff and members of the public who read the speech or article. Some of the speeches were sent to prominent individuals and the files include responses from professors, clergy, deans, college presidents, businessmen, publishers and editors. In addition there are letters of gratitude; requests for copies of the speech; logistics dealing with publication and distribution of speeches; mailing lists for speech distribution; and reports of a selection of comments generated by a speech or article.
    The contents of any one speech file tends to vary substantially with some containing very little materials compared to others. Of note in the subseries are drafts of speeches made by HRL in late 1940-early 1941 which became the basis for his "The American Century" article in LIFE.
    The subseries is arranged in chronological order, with a few exceptions, based on the final date of when a speech was given or the article published.
    - Subject Index to HRL's Speeches and Writings (binder 1), 1920-1966; 223113 (Box 166, Folder 6)
      Speeches and writings organized under the subject tab "America and the World."
    - Subject Index to HRL's Speeches and Writings (binder 2), 1928-1967; 223114 (Box 167, Folder 1)
      Speeches and writings organized under the subject tabs "Art & Architecture," "Education," "Far East," and "Journalism and/or Time Inc."
    - Subject Index to HRL's Speeches and Writings (binder 3), 1928-1966; 223116 (Box 167, Folder 2)
      Speeches and writings organized under the subject tabs "Law," "Religion," "Reminiscences," and "Reports on Trips."
    - Chronological Index to HRL's Speeches, Writings, and Trip Reports (2 folders), 1920-1967; 223125 (Box 167, Folder 3-4)
      Includes a portion of the 10 March 1967 issue of TIME with HRL on the cover showing the sources of quotes used in the article, and copies of correspondence regarding Walter Lippmann.
    - Lists of Speeches and Writings, circa 1962-1967; 205966 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      The timeframe of the speeches and writings on the lists span from the 1920s to 1967.
    - Untitled, Advertising Men's Club, Rochester, NY, 28 March 1928, 205967 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Untitled, Chicago, IL, November 1930, 205989 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - "The Distribution of Wealth in the U.S.," Harrisburg Chamber of Commerce, PA, 5 October 1931, 205990 (Box 28, Folder 7)
      Contains a brochure advertising the speech.
    - Untitled, Sigma Delta Chi, Des Moines, IA, 18 April 1933 (2 folders), 206017 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Untitled, Scranton, PA, 19 April 1934, 206018 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - "Introduction to This First Issue of LIFE," LIFE, 23 November 1936, 206019 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - "Introduction to This Second Issue of LIFE," LIFE, 30 November 1936, 206020 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - "The Existing Agreement Between Editor and Advertiser," American Association of Advertising Agencies Convention, White Sulphur Springs, WV, 30 April 1937, 206038 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - "What Must the Press Do to Meet Its Public Responsibility?," Institute of Human Relations, Williamstown, MA, 2 September 1937, 1935-1937; 206046 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Untitled, New York City Cancer Committee, NY, 27 October 1937, 206067 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Untitled, Stamford Community Chest, CT, 28 October 1937, 206068 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - "Industry and Freedom," Group 9, Ohio Bankers Association, Cleveland, 10 November 1937, 206070 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      Includes a memorandum where HRL praises Walter Lippmann.
    - Untitled, Yale Club of Montclair, NJ, 4 December 1937, 206071 (Box 29, Folder 2)